Guide to the David Miller Audio Collection ALBA.AUDIO.071
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David Miller Audio Collection
1975-1976
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Miller, David, 1908-1977
ALBA.AUDIO.071
0.1 Linear Feet 13 audio cassettes
David Miller (1908-1977), a lawyer from the Bronx, sailed for Spain as a volunteer for the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in April 1938. In the course the war he conducted radio broadcasts from Albacete and Madrid for the Voice of Spain. While in Spain he trained at Madrigueras and Tarazona with Edward Lending (1912-2003), another Lincoln Brigade volunteer. Lending later served in the United States Army during World War II. Vincent Lossowski (1914- 1984) fought with the Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War and served with the Office of Strategic Services (OSS) in World War II, organizing anti-Nazi guerilla actions under the direction of General William Donovan. He had met Lending in Spain and they remained friends. The collection consists of 13 audiocassettes, of two interviews conducted by David Miller with his friends and fellow vets, Lending and Lossowski. The discussion focuses on how they came to join the International Brigades, their experiences in Spain, and what happened after they returned.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 13 audiocassettes. They contain two interviews conducted by David Miller in response to a project initiated by Victor Berch, the archivist for the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) collection when it was housed at Brandeis University (before 2001). Berch was interested in recording autobiographical data on as many International Briagdes veterans as he could. Lincoln Brigade veteran David Miller decided to assist in this project by interviewing his friends and fellow veterans, Edward Lending and Vincent Lossowski. The taped discussions focus on how they came to join the Lincoln Brigade, their experiences in Spain, and what happened after they returned. Six of the tapes are of Lending alone, and the other seven have both Lossowski and Lending speaking (with the main focus on Lossowski). Partial transcripts are available for both interviews. The transcript of the Lossowski/Lending interview is in the John Gerassi Papers (ALBA 18). The interview of Edward Lending alone is in the Lending Papers (ALBA 68), which also contains extensive correspondence between Lending and David Miller discussing the upcoming interview and what would be done with it, their mutual interest in Israel, and their views on the leadership of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Briagade.
Historical/Biographical Note
David Miller (1908-1977), a lawyer from the Bronx, joined the Communist Party in 1932 and sailed for Spain in April 1938. In the course the war he conducted radio broadcasts from Albacete and Madrid for the Voice of Spain. While in Spain he trained at Madrigueras and Tarazona with Edward Lending. After returning from Spain he split form the Communist Party. He found himself in a state of tension with the leaders of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) and for a period was out of contact with the organization. He was close with Fredericka Martin and helped her with research and encouragement on her book about the American Medical Bureau's activities in Spain. He took a great interest in the VALB archive at Brandeis University and was in touch with the archivist Victor Berch. Miller was also a supporter of Israel and bonded in this area with fellow Vet Edward Lending. A dream of his was to visit Israel and record the life stories of the Spanish veterans living there; unfortunately he passed before this could occur.
Edward Isaac Lending (1912-2003) fought with the International Brigades in Spain and later served in the United States Army during World War II. After returning to the U.S. in December 1938, Lending became a member of the Executive Board of the Veterans of the Abraham Brigade (VALB).While Lending had been devoted to the Communist Party between 1935 and 1943, his disillusionment with policy dictated by Soviet Party leadership had been growing at least since the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact in 1939 to the point where he completely severed ties with the Party in 1943. Around this time Lending also grew critical of the VALB organization for what he perceived to be its rigid political orthodoxy. Another effort to which Lending devoted much time and energy was raising awareness of Jewish participation in the Spanish Civil War. In this he found a partner in David Miller.
Vincent Lossowski (1914- 1984) fought with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War and served with the Office of Strategic Services (OSS) in World War II under the direction of General William Donovan helping to organize anti-Nazi guerrilla actions. He left the Army with the rank of captain in 1945 and was presented with the Legion of Merit. In the 1950s Lossowski was investigated by a Congressional Military Affairs Subcommittee because of his activities in Spain and his ongoing association with the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). In his later years, Lossowski granted interviews and gave lectures to local college groups about the International Brigades and American participation in the Spanish Civil War. He remained an active member of VALB until his death in 1984 at the age of 70. He had met Lending in Spain and they remained friends.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Vincent Lossowski Papers (ALBA 071) Edward Isaac Lending Papers (ALBA 068) David Miller Papers (ALBA 076) John Gerassi Papers (ALBA 018) Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA) Vertical Files: Individuals (ALBA VF 2) Fredericka Martin Papers (ALBA 001)
Provenance
This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The audiovisual materials in the collection were digitized by the Barbara Goldsmith Preservation and Conservation Department in 2019. Digital access copies are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Americans |z Spain |x History |y 20th century.; Audiocassettes.; Lossowski, Vincent, 1914-1984; Lending, Edward Isaac, 1912-2003
- Lending, Edward; interviewed by David Miller (tape 1 of 6), Jul 4-5, 1975; cuid14439 (Drawer 3, Item 71-001, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14439)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette
  Preservation note: Due to advanced degradation of the audiocassette tape, only 10 minutes of Side 1 could be captured.
- Lending, Edward; interviewed by David Miller (tape 2 of 6), Jul 4-5, 1975; cuid14440 (Drawer 3, Item 71-002, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14440)
  Preservation note: Due to advanced degradation of the audiocassette tape, only 11 minutes of Side 1 and 4 minutes of Side 2 could be captured.
- Lending, Edward; interviewed by David Miller (tape 3 of 6), Jul 4-5, 1975; cuid14441 (Drawer 3, Item 71-003, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14441)
  Preservation note: Due to advanced degradation of the audiocassette tape, only 10 secs. of Side 1 could be captured.
- Lending, Edward; interviewed by David Miller (tape 4 of 6), Jul 4-5, 1975; cuid14442 (Drawer 3, Item 71-004, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14442)
  Preservation note: Due to advanced degradation of the audiocassette tape, only 6 minutes of Side 1 could be captured.
- Lending, Edward; interviewed by David Miller (tape 5 of 6), Jul 4-5, 1975; cuid14443 (Drawer 3, Item 71-005, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14443)
  Preservation note: Due to advanced degradation of the audiocassette tape, only 14 minutes of Side 1 could be captured.
- Lending, Edward; interviewed by David Miller (tape 6 of 6), Jul 4-5, 1975; cuid14444 (Drawer 3, Item 71-006, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14444)
  Preservation note: Due to advanced degradation of the audiocassette tape, only 6 minutes of Side 1 and 7 minutes of Side 2 could be captured.
- Lossowski, Vincent; Edward Lending; interviewed by David Miller (tape 1 of 7), Jan 26-Jan 27, 1976; cuid14445 (Drawer 3, Item 071- 007, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14445)
  Duration: 64 minutes
  Preservation note: This tape may be a duplicate made by placing a tape recorder next to a playback deck ("open air" dubbing).
- Lossowski, Vincent; Edward Lending; interviewed by David Miller (tape 2 of 7), Jan 26-Jan 27, 1976; cuid14446 (Drawer 3, Item 071- 008, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14446)
- Lossowski, Vincent; Edward Lending; interviewed by David Miller (tape 3 of 7), Jan 26-Jan 27, 1976; cuid14447 (Drawer 3, Item 071- 009, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14447)
  Duration: 63 minutes
- Lossowski, Vincent; Edward Lending; interviewed by David Miller (tape 4 of 7), Jan 26-Jan 27, 1976; cuid14448 (Drawer 3, Item 071- 010, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14448)
- Lossowski, Vincent; Edward Lending; interviewed by David Miller (tape 5 of 7), Jan 26-Jan 27, 1976; cuid14449 (Drawer 3, Item 071- 011, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14449)
  Duration: 62 minutes
- Lossowski, Vincent; Edward Lending; interviewed by David Miller (tape 6 of 7), Jan 26-Jan 27, 1976; cuid14450 (Drawer 3, Item 071- 012, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14450)
- Lossowski, Vincent; Edward Lending; interviewed by David Miller (tape 7 of 7), Jan 26-Jan 27, 1976; cuid14451 (Drawer 3, Item 071- 013, E-records tamwag_alba_audio071, E-records cuid14451)